foreign
likes to repeat the where we are you
know remind you where we are we're about
to enter the two great branches uh one
going off into the mine only school one
going off into the madimika school
belief about how to interpret things and
in the mine only School we're going to
have the
uh Lord Buddha's own commentary on what
he meant in the Citrus and then uh they
were going to have the actual Suitor
sections and they're going to be
followed by Jets and Compass commentary
on those sections and then after that we
reached the the Sutra of uh unending
never-ending wisdom and then there from
there we're going to learn the magic
Mika Viewpoint so just to remind you
we're starting off with dode Gonda which
is the Buddha's own commentary on what
he meant and then the commentary on that
by Jets and covers
foreign
uh the very first of the three
categories that we're going to discuss
now uh is called uh a question regarding
apparent inconsistencies in the sutras
and generally speaking it's impossible
for an enlightened being to be
inconsistent to say one thing in one
suture and to say another thing later
that doesn't match each other but if you
take the sutras literally if you look at
the wording itself it appears that the
Lord Buddha has contradicted himself in
different sutras like he said one thing
one at one place anybody said something
different and if you take them literally
then the Buddha seems to be
contradicting itself so someone is going
to ask the Buddha a question concerning
why did you do that you know are you
being contradictory or what isn't and
he's going to ask a question about the
three turnings of the wheel the Buddha
turned the wheel of the Dharma three
times in his in his career in his
teaching career the first second we'll
get into it what the meanings are but
there were three periods of his teaching
three great turnings of the wheel and
someone's going to ask the Buddha
question about why does the first
turning of the wheel what you said
during the first turning of the wheel
seems to contradict what you said during
the second turn of the wheel or rather
the reverse right what you said the
second time didn't matter what you said
the first time you see me to contradict
yourself we know you can't contact
yourself so what did you mean when you
said that and there's a section in the
in the in the book called the Buddha
making a commentary on his own Sutra
right where uh it's called the chapter
that was asked by the bodhisattva named
so this is a a certain bodhisattva on
our behalf you know represent he says
representing all of us students they're
going to happen throughout history you
know he asked the Buddha why did you
appear to contradict yourself when you
taught the when you turned the wheel on
these different occasions and that'll be
the first section which is called a
question regarding a parent
inconsistencies in the Buddha's own
presentation
third line from the bottom
points out that of course we'll go into
more detail later I'm just giving you a
rough a rough out of where we're going
uh the second section in the second
section that is to come the Buddha will
give his response and he'll say well you
know and I taught it that way I had this
in mind because there were those
students there and when I taught it
later I had this in mind and I taught it
a little bit differently because those
students were there and the Buddha will
explain the apparent inconsistencies in
his own presentation
foreign
explaining to you what the Buddha meant
when he was referring to the three
Essences uh the three essential Natures
these are called the three
characteristics or the three Natures
which are very special to the mind-only
school so so the Buddha in his response
is going to say well you know when I was
teaching this group who turns out to be
the mind only school right uh I had to
bring I had to use the idea of the three
essential natures and uh later on
Jessica has to explain what are these
Central nature studies referring to what
are these three special characteristic
studies referring to when the Buddha
gives his response and says yeah when I
taught this group knowing that their
minds were in such and such a condition
I had to refer to a thing called the
three essential and and I was using that
as a vehicle when I gave my presentation
to to a certain group so Jessica's going
to go into more on whether those three
essential characteristics and this is
really the guts of the Mind only School
uh
somebody's buying somebody's selling and
you have this exchange going on you know
like one guy is making an offer the
other guy's accepting it and then he'll
make an offer and he's accepting then
finally after you have this exchange
there's a profit that comes out of it
like some kind of result of the
transaction so he says in a similar you
know it's similar here that after this
exchange of questions and answers people
are asking the Buddha what do you mean
when you seem to conduct yourself and
then the Buddha answers back and out of
this exchange is produced a clear
picture of what the Buddha really meant
all along so that's like our profit out
of all this financial transactions so
you can look upon the first and second
turnings of the wheel as since they are
somewhat they have to be interpreted
they're not meant literally they were
the Buddha uh saying things that maybe
uh he didn't exactly mean literally by
the time you get to the third turning of
the wheel he's explaining he's finished
explaining the first two so the third
turning of the wheel is the one that's
the real one where he really says what
he literally meant and in the first two
are sort of these exchanges so the third
turning of the wheel or what's called
here is jupitan which is like the result
of the transaction or or what you get
out of the exchange the thing that that
is arrived at after the exchange is
going to be the third turning of the
wheel and then and in there you find out
finally due to the questions and answers
you find out the the conclusion uh at
the end through the exchange so the
fourth category will be the conclusion
resulting from The Exchange okay
I'm just giving you a general picture of
each of the categories that we're going
to be going through you won't really
appreciate the whole category until we
get there and we get the whole
explanation but I just want you to be
able to see the overall picture and then
get in your mind uh some kind of a seed
for understanding the whole thing when
you get to it later
page four
uh by the way in the monastery the great
monks memorize this whole book it's
considered so important that they
memorize the whole thing so it's in his
mind you know so he's like he says this
whole thing is the question that's posed
to the Buddha okay that hope
chunk he's a doctor means chunk that
whole chunk there was his question
posted the Buddha and that is the chunk
that's proposed to the Buddha okay
he also advised me that I could go over
the wording with you later but he wants
you to get the meaning so he says we'll
do you can do wording later with them
but I'm going to say this chunk after
that chunk means this you know and
that's what he's gonna that's what he's
gonna do it he says uh you know you
can't blame me for doing a horse race
because you guys don't have much time
when you turn the wheel the first time
when you talk to Diamond the first time
his first great period of teaching he
said didn't you say that and what
exactly did you mean when you say that
did you say that or didn't you say that
okay he's posing a question
oh
foreign
Lord Buddha has covered seven different
discrete subjects during the first
steering wheel the first one being the
five heaps or the five skandas the five
parts to a person I hope I can remember
this second one being the 12 ayodonus
which is the basically your sense organs
and your six consciousnesses and their
objects uh third one being somebody
somebody
uh the 12 Links of dependence is the
third one
the fourth subject was the 18th
categories come oh sorry number four was
the four different kinds of sustenance
okay number five number five was the
four Arya truth number how come your
views it comes number six is what we
call the 18 categories of existence
and then uh number six is this 37
components of Enlightenment okay so uh
that's the subject of the first term
real is summarized in those seven
sections
uh now you could go into dividing out
those there's divisions of 3 to 707
there's the division is a four of those
seven and seven divisions of five
divisions of eight you can go into a
long spill on just those seven divisions
I mean you could discuss the content of
those seven divisions but that's not the
point here the point is that at the end
of all ends the Buddha after during the
first turn of the wheel referred to all
the divisions of all those sevens and
said they exist by definition they exist
in truth they have their own independent
existence and the Buddha said that
during the first hearing the wheel
that's the question we have to look at
you know that's the part of the first
turn in the world that we're really
concerned with here we're not going to
go into all of those components and all
of those categories and I think the
question here is did the Buddha say
those things exist by definition by
definition from their own side truly in
truth you know did he say that and what
did he mean because no matter what he
taught during the first turn in the
wheel all of those seven categories and
all the details of those seven
categories he said one thing about all
of them he said they all Exist by
definition they all exist from their own
side they all exist in truth
listen
so uh page five first line uh is the
Buddha starting out in a question being
posed to the Buddha about look you you
talked about the five parts of every
being of beings and then you went on to
say that they existed by definition
meaning this means from their own side
independently so you you seem to have
said that when you refer to the five
heaps and this is part of the question
here foreign
the kitchen
uh so when the Buddha taught about the
five parts of a person he did so by
describing five characteristics of the
five parts of a person okay so those
five parts of a normal person have five
characteristics the first characteristic
being that he said they exist by
definition they have some kind of true
existence he said in the first training
wheel
secondly he said they have a quality of
having begun of having started of having
been created okay thirdly he said they
have a quality of being destroyed of
coming to an end
thirdly he said they have a quality of
being abandoned and here uh uh guess not
started out by saying um abandon can
have different meanings in general
sooner or later you're going to have to
abandon them uh the five heaps these
five heaps that we have the Mortal ones
that are bound to suffer Bound to Die
you will have to give them up you'll
have to abandon them in that sense and
as you get higher in the past and as
they start to transform then you get
parts of them that you don't have to
abandon anymore that's one way of
explaining quality number one four right
but the other way of explaining quality
number four when you say abandon or to
give up it could be referring to the
five heaps as they as they regard to the
first of the uh sorry second of the Four
Noble Truths which is the source of
suffering so he says if you look at the
five parts of a person from the
Viewpoint of the second are your truth
right uh then you you see that they are
the source of suffering you see how the
source of suffering relates to the five
heaps and that's it's very famous in the
sutures when the Buddha says you have to
eliminate Arya truth number two you have
to get rid of it you see the source of
suffering is something that should be
gotten rid of and then what he said
about the fourth Noble Truth fourth on
your truth is that I'm sorry the first
Iron truth is that this is something you
should must realize is going on what's
number one
suffered so he said you have to realize
what's going on so your relationship to
the first are you true should be to
realize it in relationship to the
secondary truth should be to eliminate
it so with regard to the five skandas or
the five parts to a person the first
characteristic that the Buddha said was
they exist from their own side they have
their own true existence then he said
they start then he said they stop then
he said with regard to the source of
suffering
quality that they have you have to get
rid of it with regard to the the truth
of suffering called it that they have
which is that they are suffering you
have to realize what's going on you have
to understand that they are suffering
okay so those are the five
characteristics the Buddha used to
describe the five heaps but the first of
those is that they exist by definition
they do exist from their own side
um
is asking Lord Buddha hey and you said
the same things when you taught the
second big subject which was those 12
I had done as the 12 uh we call them the
doors of uh existence or something like
that meaning uh things occur through the
presence of your sense Powers okay uh
the gates of of existence or something
you can call them the 12 gates when you
got to the 12 gates which is just
another way of dividing up people
instead of five heaps you can say 12
gifts when you got to the 12 gates you
went through the same five
characteristics with them
okay and then when you got on to the 12
lengths of dependent intonation you went
through the five parts with them two
five parts meaning they do exist from
their own side they began they stop they
have their own source of suffering they
have their own suffering which you
should realize okay
and when you discovered the four kinds
of sustenance you also discussed them in
those five characteristics so you
applied those five characteristics to
your discussion of each one of those
different subjects the five heaps the
twelve doors of sense the five were the
12 uh parts of Defender intonation and
then the four kinds of sustenance but
whatever you taught in the first turn of
the wheel you said that it had those
five characteristics and the first
characteristic was that it existed on
its own of its own accord by definition
so for all four of those uh
different categories you said all five
are completed in each one of those four
when you got to the four audio truths
which was his fifth subject right in the
first turn in the wheel you discussed it
in terms of two divisions rather than
five
and when you got to the foreign truth
the one thing you definitely said about
them was that they do have their own
true existence they do exist from their
own side they do have a definitive
existence they exist by definitions
jobs
we said that each of the four noble
truths for Arya truth had two
characteristics each and here's how it
comes out to two each uh the first one
is the truth of suffering and your
relationship to that has to be that you
have to realize that that's going on so
in the Sutra it says the truth of
suffering is something to be realized or
something that you have to understand is
really happening otherwise you can't get
anywhere you have to realize that the
truth of suffering is going on that's
your relationship to this First Eye of
Truth your relationship to the secondary
truth which comes naturally because you
think of yourself why am I suffering is
is the secondary truth being the source
of suffering and your relationship to
that Source has to be I want to get rid
of it I want to eliminate it okay then
you should come up in your mind is it
possible to stop it entirely can I stop
suffering entirely yes and that's a
truth number three and your relationship
to truth number three should be to bring
it about the end of suffering and your
relationship to truth number four which
It comes naturally oh how do I bring it
about is which is the path is to
practice the path to carry out the path
so there are four Arya truths you have a
different relationship to each one and
then each of those separate
relationships is the first
characteristic of the true truth so for
example for the normal truth of
suffering your relation the first
characteristic is you have to know
what's going on
Noble Truth of the source of suffering
the first characteristic is you have to
understand that it's happening I'm sorry
uh get rid of it okay the relationship
to the third Noble Truth and and also
its first characteristic is that you
want to achieve it and your relationship
to the fourth Noble Truth which is its
first characteristic is that you want to
practice it that's the first
characteristics of each one of the four
are your twos what's the second
characteristic which is actually the
first one stated is that they all Exist
by definition they all exist truly so
the Buddha said those two things about
each one so each one has its own unique
characteristic and then all four have
their common characteristic which is
that the Buddhist said that exist by
definition exists from its own side
foreign
there's two there's four characteristics
that Lord Buddha taught with regard to
the 18 categories okay but here he
doesn't say 18 characters it just says
categories okay so the first time he
says categories he says
which means uh the six categories not
the eighteen okay so when he says uh
category is the first time or the first
character of the categories is the six
categories these are the uh
they were talking about the four
elements uh earth water
uh fire wind Consciousness and space and
that's one of the six those are called
the six daughters or the six comes or
the six categories so that's the first
characteristic of the categories
is when he discusses them in terms of
six when he discusses the categories
again he discusses them in terms of 18
which is the six objects of the of them
census the sixth census and the six
consciousness of the senses so then you
get 18.
then he went on to say you have to get
rid of something don't you and there is
referring to the 18 categories with
reference to there being uh
the source of suffering okay because
that's the the when you when you're
talking about the 18 parts of existence
and you're identifying certain pieces of
those parts as being something you have
to get rid of you're talking about the
component of the noble truth of the
source of suffering which they have
okay then when you get on to Jones ship
or it means you have to realize meaning
you have to just get it that there are
Parts among these 18 categories of all
existence that you have to realize what
realize that they are suffering so now
he's applying that to the first number
two so Lord Buddha in the first turn of
the wheel teaches the categories of
existence in four different ways he says
you can divide them into six
and divide them into 18
you can you can look at them in terms of
what you have to eliminate which is a
source of suffering and you can look at
them in terms of the source of suffering
itself which is something you have to
just realize is going on and that's
that's how you Lord Buddha taught the
the categories of existence he's still
posing his question okay
uh
correction okay
the first of the four is the 18 and come
Duma the second of the four is the sixth
I said sixth first and 18 second which
is what he said the first and then he
then he said well now you have to it's
really not simple it means 18 which is
the first so first he taught the
categories he's 18. then you talk to
categories of six then you discuss the
categories in terms of the source of
suffering that you have to eliminate
with them and then you taught the
categories in terms of the suffering
which you just have to realize is going
on okay and that's his presentation
that's the Lord Buddha's way of
presenting the categories
he wants to go over the 18 categories
with you and make sure you understand
this is uh I'll be done with first
chapter
I want to explain the 18 to you well
it's 6 times 3 is 18.
six times
maybe you want to know what the sinks
are
um
there are uh six uh receptors
uh six sensors that a human being has so
the first one is the eyes you know like
that see things the ears that pick up
things it's audible things the nose that
smells and smellable things uh the
tongue that tastes tastable things the
body which senses tangible things and
then your mind let's see oh you guys
think it's up here
like this that that understands things
and so these are the basically the six
sensors or the six receptors that are
the being has
uh so there are about there are six
different sensors meaning understanders
he says that things are going on and
they are sitting on six different chairs
they need a chair to sit on don't they I
mean they need to do sit and do their
work so six people who know what's going
on have to have six seats to sit on
so you can think of six chairs on which
the sixth sensor beings are sitting and
those six chairs are the are the sense
organs and he says for example with the
eye there's the eye ball but I don't
think that's the sense organ that's not
the sense organ itself the sense organ
itself is the optical is the cells at
the back of the eyes that that uh are
receptors and and which are sensitive to
forms and colors and I guess you're a
scientists have figured it out by now uh
he says but but it's not the eyeball per
se it's the it's the it's the sensitive
cells included at the back of the eye
which is the chair on which the center
the seeing sensor sits and then the the
ear has its similar chair the nose has a
chair like that the tongue has a chair
like that the body and then like foreign
uh which are to be sensed so he talked
about sensors or receptors and now he's
talking about the receptivities the
recept things to be received and the
things to be sensed and that also has
six divisions so in the case of the eye
you are sensing shapes and colors in the
case of the ear you're hearing noises in
the sense of the nose you are you know
uncensing sounds and then in the sense
of the nose you're smelling certain
objects you are tasting certain objects
you are feeling certain objects and then
with regard to the mind you are
perceiving certain objects which are not
included into the other five so the
object is in mind is not tastes or
colors or sounds like that it is what we
call Dharma and that's in this case
Dharma means all those objects which are
not covered by the other five and that
come or that category is called tamadatu
and that's the real meaning of dominant
is the is the category of things which
the Mind sensor is sensing when he sits
on his chair of the sense the Mind sense
organ and he's and he's looking out and
he's thinking about things that cannot
be described by the senses alike the
concept of impermanence or the concept
of something growing uh Concepts or
facts or truths are objects of the
mental sense and that way you get
eighteen six sensors sitting on six
chairs of the sense organs uh focusing
on six Sensations that they are looking
at well that will give the other one
that's the 18 categories
so we finished six of the seven uh
divisions of the first novel uh of the
first turning of the wheel
s
uh the seventh of the subjects of the
first turn in the wheel is called the 37
callings of Enlightenment those can be
divided into seven groups and when you
add them all up they add up to 37.
foreign
among 37 qualities Enlightenment in the
37 colonies there are seven uh different
groups
follow me
uh 37 Enlightenment qualities divided
into seven groups uh and then each of
them having their own uh it divides out
to 37 but he's saying they're going to
have eight characteristics okay so
whether you treat them as 37 individual
members or whether you treat them in
regards of seven groups uh they have
eight characteristics and then he went
through the seven groups uh
the four recollections
the four
before perfect abandonments how's that
okay
uh the four legs the four miraculous
legs okay they just have names like this
uh the five powers
the five powers in the 37 don't return
to the five powers in the 18 okay
they're not refer to the sense Powers
they're talking about powers of a Buddha
and then the five forces of a Buddha
and that adds up to 37 hopefully
oh sorry we missed the uh eight uh
components of the Oregon path that
should add up to 37. I think it's four
four four five five and eight so it's
four three times four is twelve two
times five is ten that's 22.
and then the problem you're not gay
that's 30.
uh and the seven limbs of Enlightenment
okay so then you get 37 which is
somewhere it's probably before the eight
parts of the audio path it is not the
main subject here he says
whether you treat these 37 individually
or whether you treat them in groups that
total seven groups
each of the 37 as individually or the 37
in the seven groups uh has eight
characteristics but the one that covers
all of them is the same as the first one
and all the others which is they exist
from their own side they exist by
definition the exist in truths okay
foreign
uh okay now you get the seven remaining
ones of the eight qualities that are
that are shared by the 37 colonies which
is the seventh category right okay so
here they go
uh the first quality of the eight was
that they were existed from their own
side or by definition right the second
one is called mitumba mitumba means uh
not getting along with one another uh
fighting with each other and what it
refers to is the fact that although the
37 qualities are all wonderful each one
of them has its own enemy right so for
example if you take love its enemy might
be hatred so the quality of discordance
applies to all 37 meaning they don't
Concord with their opposites they don't
get along with their opposites there's a
hassle there's a fight out Punch Out
going on between and he he says it that
way he likes to say things I think he
says there's a punch out going on
between love and anger so there's an
idea that there's a discordance going on
with all of the 37 each one of the 37th
seven has a quality of discordance where
it's fighting against the quality which
is negative and that's the discordance
it's the second quality of all 37.
foreign
so if you
really you should name number two the
enemy okay I mean Timber means uh the
the opposite in literally in tibetan
means the opposite so quality number one
again is exists in truth or by
definition quality number two is it has
its enemy and quality number three is
called counter agent or antidote or
fixed and that that refers to each of
the 37 acts as its antidote or its fixed
for one of those negative for its
corresponding negativity which is number
two right okay
uh
um
uh each one of the 37 also has a quality
of uh creating what was not created
before or causing what was not caused
before or giving you something that you
didn't have before so it's called means
to bring about something that wasn't
brought out brought about yet meaning
that each time you get one of these 37
qualities it enables you to
to engender in yourself spiritual
qualities that you haven't yet
engendered so the third quality shared a
fourth one right shared by all 37 is
that it engenders that which has not yet
been engendered okay
yeah
uh now we're on to the West six quality
once you have engendered a good
spiritual quality they Empower you to
maintain it and he says most of us we
get some beginning of a spiritual good
quality and it's almost as if a Mugger
mugs us and takes it away from us they
always tend to degenerate you know but
once you get into these 37 qualities of
Enlightenment then then you have each
one of them has the power to help you
maintain the good spiritual quality
which you have previously engendered so
that which is not engendered gun
engendered and that which was engendered
is being maintained
foreign
uh there's a there's a the next one is
called metibor which is an ancient term
he says it's a it's an anachronism for
the idea of uncuttable un or Inseparable
and what it means is that once you have
a good spiritual quality once you've
been able to maintain the good spiritual
quality then no matter which one of the
37 good qualities it is once you get
into it this is a characteristic of all
37 that allows you to keep yourself from
being separated from this good quality
and going off to some bad quality so
it's like some kind of inseparability uh
that doesn't allow you to be cut off
from it and wander off to its negative
to the negative side so it's called it's
an ancient word we're going to get into
these words in more detail later but and
it comes later the words you won't find
them right here at this section because
this quality is that you will not be
separated or you'll not be cut off from
this good quality that you've been able
to maintain you will constantly be
connected to that good quality
foreign
meaning uh it's self-perpetuating and
self-improving so once you get any one
of these 37 qualities each one of those
37 qualities has a has its own quality
of of improving itself constantly I
don't this tape stuff maybe I'm not sure
uh that that that's quality number seven
and once you get into any one of the 37
qualities it is self-perpetuating
self-improving uh it has a
self-improving quality to it it keeps
going better and better
foreign
number seven had this idea of getting
higher and higher getting better and
better number eight is like it gets
broader and broader or wider and wider
so once you have one of those 37
qualities uh it tends to be
self-widening uh self-increasing on a
horizontal sort of uh feeling and the
other one is this number seven was sort
of getting higher and higher so this is
like ever ever
fattening ever widening you know and it
just keeps getting wider and wider okay
like that more fast
those are the eight qualities uh shared
by the 37 uh components of enlightenment
foreign
categories
of teachings and then you went on to
this long story about how they have all
these separate characteristics
characters they have characteristic
division after division you talked about
it over and over again but there's one
thing that all of them had in common
there's one thing you kept saying about
all of them and that was that they
existed by definition they existed from
their own side they had some kind of
true existence you repeated that quality
in every single one of these seven
groups you repeated it for every single
component of these seven groups now what
I want to ask you Lord Buddha about is
that one you know when you got to that
what were you talking about when you
said oh they exist by definition or from
their own side
uh so if you take the whole question
that the police I was asking separate
out all those other uh details that we
talked about let's isolate this idea of
them existing from their own side or by
definition now let's talk about that
let's let's focus on that quality
uh and all of this is stuff that you
Lord Buddha said in the first turning of
the wheel and in the first turn of the
wheel if we isolate out the one quality
that you seem to be pressing on it was
that things had some kind of natural
existence or existence from their own
side
now we're getting to our second section
uh if we read out from page five six
line from the bottom there's a sentence
that begins with Chum then day and he
says uh Buddha then you got into the the
second turning of the wheel which we
sometimes call the the uh
the in-between turning of the wheel
sometimes it's given that name so when
you got to the in between turning of the
wheel meaning the second turn of the
wheel then Lord Buddha you said
something totally different
yeah
uh then when you got to the the middle
turning of the wheel which always means
the second one right when you got to the
middle turning the wheel right after you
had finished the first three of the
wheel where you mentioned the seven
groups and all these things everything
from a person's physical form which is
the first of the five parts or skandas
all the way up to the 37 colonies of
Enlightenment all from between there you
said one thing they all do have their
own true existence they all do have
their independent in existence and then
when you got to the Secretary of the
wheel you reversed yourself and you said
there is nothing in the universe that
has any natural existence there's
nothing in the universe that exists from
its own side there's nothing in the
universe that has any true kind of
existence then then that's what you said
during the secretary of the real
chance
and the wording you used during the
secretary of the wheel was that things
don't start of their own accord that was
the the wording you used meaning they
don't exist by definition they don't
exist from their own side they don't
exist in truth the wording he used was
things don't start as their own accord
foreign
then you said they don't start you said
nothing starts no object in the universe
starts but what you meant when you said
that in the second term in the world was
nothing starts of its own accord nothing
starts by definition
then you said those things which stop
forget the things which start then you
said nothing which stops starts from its
own other side either so you use that
kind of wording during the second turn
in the wheel
uh peace from the beginning peace from
the beginning of our beginnings peace
for all time means peace for all time
but when you said that what you meant
was no object in the universe has any
existence from its own side or of its
own accord and and you use that kind of
language too
then the fifth quality that you
mentioned in the second turning of the
wheel right we finished four the fifth
quality that you mentioned in the second
turn in the wheel was that uh everything
is gone beyond grief remember this is
the Tibetan word for Nirvana really but
here it has a special meaning says grief
here means its own true existence and
when you say everything has gone beyond
that you're meaning that no object in
the universe is such that it hasn't gone
beyond its own to existence meaning that
nothing has any true existence nothing
exists from its own side so now during
the second turn of the wheel you use
five different descriptions five
different qualities which all basically
refer to the same thing
uh I want to ask you a question I want
you to give me an answer uh so you think
about it we don't need to look at the
book or anything like that I want you to
consider the following question in the
first turning of the wheel this
enlightened being says uh nothing has
any natural or true existence of its own
then in the secretary of the wheel the
same enlightened being same guy says
nothing has any natural existence
nothing it's impossible for anything to
have any natural existence of its own so
so what do you think we have a problem
here or or not you know we have an
enlightened being who's saying two
completely opposite things what do you
think is going on here
woman
from here
first I ask you the following question
is there a contradiction in the wording
or not
forget the meaning is there a
contradiction in the wording
yeah
uh why is it contradictory
in the wording that is weird what makes
it what makes it contradictory in the
morning
he'd like you to repeat the words that
you think are contradictory could you
tell me what's what he said in the first
give me any example of what he said in
the first turn in the wheel that
contradicts any specific example from
the secretary of the will he says give
me this you said oh in the wording it's
called Victory hey give me some wording
for the first one it's contradictory
some kind of wording from the second one
thank you
foreign
laughs
and then close the door he says
he says you guys
he says we all got different uh mind
streams and he's going out
today
foreign
second
uh
only School in person it's very
suspicious they think to say oh
everything from physical matter on up
doesn't have any existence of its own
accord they start thinking uh-oh you
guys are nihilers you guys are you guys
are denying the existence of everything
so other when they are confronted with
this contradiction of the Buddha saying
first everything does have some natural
existence or some existence of his own
accord and then he says secondly nothing
has any natural existence or existence
of its own accord and when they're
confronted with this apparent
contradiction they start to doubt the
second turn in the world they start to
say I I kind of don't like that one
because that one sounds like saying that
none of these objects has any existence
at all
it's awesome
uh being like a mind-only school this
body stop is sort of tending towards the
mind only school so the one he's going
after is the secretary of the wheel he's
like pressing the Buddha on his question
is pressing the Buddha on the second one
he's saying now what a misunderstanding
about what Lord Lord Buddha meant when
he talked about existing by definition
or non-existing by definition and in
this next section uh Jetson copper is
addressing this misunderstanding that
came up during the commentario tradition
foreign
uh there was a commentator that is
called in tibetan the great Chinese or
the great Chinese commentary and uh he
says his name in tibetan is docselves in
complete cell mean and clear and he
believes that the Chinese were the
corresponding word is called wencik and
he was a a great commentator he did a
comment extensively on that Sutra which
is the content of the third turn of the
wheel which is where the Buddha tried to
explain what he meant in the sutras
right dode Gonzo which is uh called the
commentary by Lord Buddha on running men
in the Citrus and when uh this
commentator the great the great
he's called uh when he got to this point
about the word that kept coming up
existing by definition existing by
definition he took it to mean literally
a definition in the sense of defining an
object you know like fire beating hot
and burning or something like that he
took it to mean of the the concept of
defining an object he took it to mean
the literal definition of a thing
existing through its The Words which
Define it or something like that he took
it that way
uh in general later on there will come
the three great attributes or the three
great qualities that are the like the
central theme of the Mind only school
one of them is called kuntak which means
to exist in name only or to be nominal
and uh the idea is of something being
nominal is that it doesn't have any true
existence of its own uh
in general the mind only School says
that the concept of things existing only
nominally or nominal the concept of
nominal can be explained as non-existing
by its definition
and he would have taken that to mean
nominal means doesn't have a definition
you see I mean so there's a big
difference between not existing by
definition and not having a definition
so if you take it the way he took it
then Justin copper says you have a
problem that when the mind only school
gets to
explaining the idea of existing
nominally or nominal things
then since they described that as
non-existing by definition then if you
uh if you explain the word definition
with the same connotation that you want
to explain it with then you'd be saying
that the mind only School says that
there are certain objects in the world
that have no definition so it can't mean
that okay um
they'll be this kind of hassle later on
says Justin copper that if you explain
the word existing by definition as
having no definition then when you get
to the mind only school's own
explanation of things that exist
nominally and they say they don't exist
by definition you're going to have to be
saying that all that stuff doesn't have
any definition at all got it foreign
uh in the third turn of the wheel they
start to talk a lot about things
existing nominally and non-existing by
definition and if they're getting into
the problem there that not existing by
definition means not having a definition
then in the mind School mind only
school's own presentation during the
third turn of the real you're going to
have this problem that they're uh
describing something as having no
definition at all so your interpretation
of what Lord Buddha means when he says
things don't exist by definition cannot
be correct when you explain it as
meaning they don't have any definition
so now we're on to page seven he's on
the second line uh our savior uh Jason
Kappa is now uh going to go through the
Sutra and identify or a few of the more
difficult words here and explain the few
of the more obscure words in this whole
big suture passage we just had so Justin
cover wants to make sure you understand
what they refer to so when The Suitor
refers to various categories that's the
one that refers to the uh 18.
categories and when it says many
categories that's the one remember we
confuse them ourselves uh when you'll
get to the six categories so when he
says various categories talking about 18
categories when he talks about many
categories he's talking about the six
categories and uh he says people have uh
explained it differently but they're
wrong this is what they this is what
they refer to okay
when we were describing among the seven
groups I believe it was the fourth one
you can check but it was number group
number four and they started talking
about the categories and there were four
uh
of the groups and they talked about the
daughters and in the situ there they say
oh the Dodgers have four qualities and
they talked about the the various
tattoos the various categories and then
he talked about the numerous categories
so when Lord Buddha says various he's
talking about the 18 categories when he
says numerous he's talking about the six
categories
and so this is one uh clarification that
Justin copper is making for you so
you're under so you appreciate the words
of the Sutra Elizabeth
is trying to help you out with a very
remember we said there was an
anachronism an ancient word called
mikupa and he's trying to help you out
with that word remember that this word
came in the explanation of the seventh
category uh the seventh part of the
seventh category right uh I'm sorry
yeah
no it was the seventh of all the groups
was the 37 callings of Enlightenment and
37 components of Enlightenment inside of
there there were seven groups if you
take them by groups and 37 if you take
them individually but the eighth quality
of all of them I think it was the eighth
quality of all 37 or all seven groups of
the 37 whether you take it that way is
that uh
you wouldn't be separated from right or
something like that it was like an is a
sixth one what was the seventh one oh no
it's a fifth one maybe
no there was widening with the last one
perpetuation was the seventh one we must
be on the sixth one yeah yeah
um
you're right number six number six and
uh Jessica here is explaining that very
rare word extremely rare word he's
saying uh the Tibetan here means not to
be separated from or not to be divided
from something Inseparable okay so
jethal God was trying to clarify that
rare word for you
uh
modus operandi is to go for the hard
spots and soften them up for us
we have completed the first section
which is where uh the bodhisattva uh
asked the question to learn Buddha now
we're on to the next
sections
so we've reached a line five page seven
and this is the second category which as
you remember is where Lord Buddha makes
his response this is when you get Lord
Buddha's answer
foreign
now Justin copper in his explanation is
going to start using the word or the
expression
and Geisha wants you to understand that
when he gets to the word which means
doesn't have any nature of its own Kappa
is mainly referring to the expression
which means doesn't have any doesn't
exist by definition so he wants you to
know that from here on when Judson Kappa
starts talking about things have no
nature of their own he's actually
referring to the expression found in the
Sutra which says things don't exist by
definition okay so we want you to
understand that from here on out when he
says they don't have their own nature
he's talking about they don't have their
they don't exist by definition in the
way that that phrase was used in the
original Sutra during the question and
and during the three turnings of the
wheel okay
expressed concern about the content of
the secretary of the wheel mainly right
the guy going on it didn't go on the
train it's not like that you know
then Lord Buddha is going to address his
response mainly to that part of the
question that was expressing doubt about
the content of the secretary of the
world we learned British said nothing
exists by definition
thank you
that is
when Lord Buddha gives his answer to the
concerns expressed by the bodhisattva
about the secretary of the will remember
there were five qualities in the
secretary of the wheel that the body
stopper was asking about the first one
being oh you said that nothing existed
by definition or not nothing
nothing's nature was possible
means nothing the nature of everything
is impossible and then he went on to
four other characterizations right so
the Buddha in his reply Lord Buddha's
reply is going to treat them the five
the five parts as one and then four so
first he's going to talk about how come
I said the nature of everything is
impossible and then how come I said
those other four things about all
existing objects what Jesus so we'll
have two sections now my name is
so there'd be two sections coming up
here first it'll be Lord Buddha
responding on why was it I said nothing
had any nature uh that the nature of
things was impossible and then why was
it that I said those other four things
starting with things don't start things
don't stop dot dot dot okay so the
answer is going to be in two parts
foreign
young qualities
so if out of the five we chop off the
last four and we're not going to talk
about them right now we're going to talk
about the first of the five which is
where Buddha said the nature of
everything is impossible the it's they
cannot have a nature like they seem to
have right which means they don't exist
by definition what did Lord when Lord
Buddha responds to that and he explains
himself he says look you're on that part
what I was meaning what I meant to say
was this when he responds his response
can be treated in three different
categories first one we're right in the
middle of page seven dorthema means
Buddha gives a lord Buddha gives a brief
response or sort of a an inclusive
response and then secondly we go on to a
a more detailed explanation of that
response and then thirdly Lord Buddha in
trying to explain himself after having
done so briefly and in more detail says
look if you don't you still don't get it
I'll give you an example you know I'll
give you some kind of concrete example
so maybe you can understand what I'm
trying to talk about okay
the answer begins with the words
which means that's that bodhisattva's
personal name so the the point here says
that Lord Buddha is trying to tell him
you know
check this out listen carefully okay I'm
I'm telling you your answer now so first
he says he addresses him by name so that
so he's alerting the bodhisattva now
listen it's time for you to listen
carefully okay because he's addressing
him by his own name okay
uh and Lord Buddha responds in the fine
way oh the niana pot here's what I meant
when I said that nothing had any nature
of its own or nothing had any that
nothing existed by definition what I
meant was that three different things
first I meant that things don't have any
uh nature of their own they don't exist
by definition secondly I meant that I'm
sorry let's say it this way they don't
have any nature of having their own
qualities they don't have any nature of
starting and they don't have any nature
of being ultimate and those are the
three things that I was talking about
when I said things don't have any nature
they don't have any nature of having any
characteristics they don't have any
nature of starting and they don't have
any nature of being ultimate and those
are the three things I had in mind when
I said things don't have any nature
what if
um
uh he says uh we're gonna insert here a
little bit of our own explanation okay
because we gotta go if we don't take a
little bit out of the concepts or the
teachings of the Mind only school now if
you don't take sort of a break right
here and explain the three qualities
that are proposed that are expounded by
the mind only school you're going to
have trouble later on so what I'm about
to say is like an aside which I would
like to insert here and we'll just kind
of insert this sort of aside so that you
guys know what Lord Buddha is talking
about in terms of the beliefs of the
Mind only School
foreign
the first of the three attributes we'll
call them attributes okay or the three
attributes of existing objects that the
mind only School talks about is called
Shenron means uh depends on others or
under others control and we can call it
uh
dependence okay or something like that
it's not the dependence of
interdependence and Arduino okay it's a
different meaning but it means uh
the dependence that things have that
refers to the objects of our everyday
world I don't have to go into a big deal
about it okay this is all what we call
Shenron this is all what we call under
the control of other things meaning
dependent on other things so when we
talk about the first attribute which is
expounded by the mind only School we're
talking about all the objects in your
normal experience are called uh
dependent okay
what condition
s
the second attribute that the minority
School talks about ain't so easy to see
not something you can see not something
you can taste or feel if you go up into
the higher schools into the into the
middleweight schools Miami maker schools
they start talking about things like
emptiness the word they use is emptiness
and that that is what the second of the
attributes refers to yongdu means
something like
total existence or something like that
but in the mind-only school the word
total existence is an expression to
describe what is in the higher schools
called emptiness so it's not something
you can see it tastes feel it's not
something in your everyday world it's
something that's a little harder to
perceive but that's the idea that they
have in mind when they talk about the
second attribute the first attribute
being dependence the second attribute
being total existence or something like
that meaning in this case something like
emptiness
foreign
uh the third attribute or the third a
bunch of objects that the the middle uh
mine only school is talking about is
called nominal stuff nominal things okay
it's called Kunta in tibetan nominal
things again is not something in your
everyday experience it's not something
around you that you can touch or feel or
that's just very familiar to you again
it's something you have to think about
he says a simple way to explain what the
mind only School means when they talk
about nominal stuff is that they are
talking about unchanging objects all the
unchanging objects in the world now you
should think wait a minute number two
was you said it was pretty much
equivalent to emptiness but that's an
unchanging job he says you're right kick
out number two and all the other
unchanging things in the world are our
general description of what we mean in
the mind-only school when we talk about
the third attribute which is uh nominal
stuff things that are just labeled
things so if you take out uh from all
the unchanging things in the universe
emptiness then the rest of the
unchanging things you have things which
do exist but which do not change those
would all be in the third category of
the third attribute which is uh talked
about by the mind only school he says an
example if you run of an unchanging
thing you know I was hoping
it's interesting because he pulled out a
new one for me uh he said indeed
the mental image you have when you're
talking about something that you haven't
seen before so he says if you talk about
you guys have just been to Mongolia
you're on your way to Russia and when
you talk about one of those countries to
me I've never been there but I get some
kind of picture in my mind and that
picture isn't kind of a a pure perfect
unchanging picture of something which is
just a an imagination of something and
although imagination although imagine
things don't exist the imagination of
the thing does exist and the imagination
of the thing is such that it doesn't
really change you know I just have this
perfect mental image of what you mean
when you say Mongolia or Russia or
something like that and that's an
example of something in in the third
category of the mind-only school when
they talk about things that are just
nominal things which exist nominally
foreign
he says when I uh when I talk about
Russia or Mongolia this way I'm not
denying the existence of Russia okay I'm
just saying I haven't experienced it
directly so when I think of Russia and I
close my eyes and you say Russia and I I
try to conjure up some image of Russia
I'm Conjuring up a Dungey right I'm
Conjuring up a mental image a perfect
little mental image of this thing that
you call Russia and and I'm getting this
thing and if we were to sit down and try
to decide is that mental image I have of
Russia a changing thing or an unchanging
thing since it's this like this made up
imagination perfect picture I have of
something it's not really changing in a
sense that that thing we we call labeled
or kundak or belonging to the third
category of the Mind only school which
means things which are just nominal
nominal stuff and that's what I mean I'm
not denying existence of the little
towns around India and stuff like that
either
the reason I'm bringing up this idea of
a perfect developmental image you know
of you know closing your eyes and trying
to get a perfect image of Russia or
something and that being unchanging the
reason I've inserted that here is that
it's going to be very useful for you in
two or three days from now when we hit
that concept and we start talking about
that concept so I thought I'd just
thrown in here
laughs
today
uh we're talking about Concepts now uh
mental ideas mental pictures and in a
sense uh the question of whether it
exists or not is really hinges on the
question of whether you've thought of it
or not you see I mean so it's when you
close your eyes and you start thinking
about Russia that the mental image of
Russia starts to exist you see what I
mean so it's uh occurrence in this world
it's being born in this order I
shouldn't say that but anyway it's it's
existence in this world is dependent
upon your closing your eyes and thinking
of it so the thing doesn't the the one
quality of a mental concept or an
imagined thing is that your thinking of
it is what makes it happen you said the
concert or the image the mental image
starts to happen when you start to think
about it now I'll give you another
example let's say you're sitting in a
class uh your legs are starting to hurt
you're starting to think about I think
two hours must have gone by by now uh I
don't know I guess that's going on for
and then you suddenly get this mental
image of your mind of your feet walking
down those steps right there and uh that
mental image didn't exist until you
start to think about it you see and then
when you start your legs start to hurt
your butt starts to hurt you start
thinking about walking down those steps
and you can actually in your mind see
your feet hitting each step until that
moment that mental image didn't exist so
if you're thinking about it which has
brought the mental image into existence
right at that moment so really these are
very slippery things whether or not they
even exist depends on whether or not it
has occurred to you
foreign
maybe some of you are having a mental
image of a cup of tea in a certain cup
that you know on a certain table over
there in general house
but right now there's no tea is there
all of those things are just created by
your own imagination really right the
current cup of tea is a is a fantasy
it's a creation of your imagination and
all that kind of stuff you can throw
into the third group of stuff that the
mind only school is talking about when
they say nominal thing nominal stuff
they all take all those things that
exist only because you just thought of
them and you can throw all those into
category number three
oh okay tradition is
so uh now we're reaching to go back to
where we start we took off our we took
off on a little tangent right now we're
coming back to the text so everything
from about seven or eight lines up from
the bottom of page seven down to the
third lineup from the bottom page seven
has been the Buddhist short answer
remember first he's going to give a
short answer so Buddha has just given uh
Lord Buddha has just given a short
answer to the question of
and then Kappa in commenting upon the
short question says uh what essentially
Lord Buddha is saying is that when I
said that things have no nature oh
bodhisattva what I meant was things
don't have any one of the three natures
and that's a short answer
foreign
is explaining in a single phrase what
the Buddha meant in a shorter answer and
remember that Justin copper has
explained the response with the one
sentence and he said what the Buddha man
when he said nothing had a nature was
nothing has anyone in the three natures
and he left you with that
and he wants to prove that when he says
when that's his characterization of the
short response of Lord Buddha now just
on copper being Judson copper has to say
and I have an authoritative source for
saying that so where does he go to does
he go to some llama into bed or one of
the more recently islamists no he goes
straight back to the founder of the Mind
only school you know the guy who really
restored it in this universe which is uh
master of Sangha so he goes straight
back to master of Sangha he goes to a
book called Dua and and he's and he's
going to take his uh proof right from
there from Master science book that his
characterization of Lord Buddha's
answers is is a pretty good one because
in a tsanga's own text he says what did
the Buddha have in mind when he said
that nothing had any nature I'll tell
you what he had in mind he meant that
nothing has any one of three different
kinds of natures that he was thinking of
and those are all uh spoken according to
the level of the student student's mind
was at a certain level so I had to
describe the lack of things the lack of
nature of things in the in terms of the
lack of three different natures and
that's why I got into three different
Natures because there are three
different kinds of disciples have
different capacities and because of the
different capacities of the disciples
when I said when I was explaining the
word no nature I explained it to them in
terms of none of three different natures
when he explained that that point and
here in in a sangha's answer it's also
in the form of a question and an answer
so asunder is saying suppose someone
came up to me as Sangha Master Sangha
and said what did the Buddha mean when
he said nothing had any nature okay no
object in the world had any nature well
I'll tell you what he said mepa means
I'll tell you what he said and now you
listen to what I'm about to say okay
that's his first part of his answer
due to the due to the disciples own mind
and and guess Allah says remember that
disciple means in tibetan means that
which is to be disciplined meaning uh
you know disciple means the disciplinary
all right in tibetan it's a it's a pun
he says remember the disciplinary
according to discipline e the
discipliner has to uh explain it I I am
trying to explain it to them in terms of
three different kinds of lack of nature
okay when I say no nature I'm referring
to three different kinds of a lack of
Nature and those three different three
different kinds of a lack of nature I
have to use because of differing levels
of my disciples
uh and then Jessica says I not only have
a Sangha to quote I have to call you
know I can call myself because he says
exactly the same thing in his 30 verses
he says what did the Buddha say mean in
the second turning of the wheel when he
said nothing has any nature of his own
he was referring to the lack of three
different kinds of Nature and that's
what the Buddha had in mind when he said
during the second turning in the wheel
that nothing has any nature of its own
so I'm not just quoting master and
Sangha I can also quote
what
is
foreign
quotation here I'm not sure that that
you're using the right quotation here
delicious
foreign
he says one important point you have to
keep in mind from here on out and don't
forget it is that we are in the mind
only school and he says I think you guys
might have had some teaching from Geisha
about the mighty Mika school middle
grade school he says one important thing
to answer in the debate that's about to
occur in in all these sections here
don't forget we're in Judson Copper's
explanation of the Mind the only
school's explanation of what's going on
and don't get confused and don't start
mixing in Mighty Mika explanations so so
one thing to keep in mind throughout the
following pages is that Jason Kappa is
in the middle way school and he's
answering everything according to the
middle way School
and and we don't go mixing uh you know
American traditions and Indian
traditions when you're in America you
follow the American tradition when
you're in the Indian tradition and you
don't mix them up so don't forget we're
in we're following the mind-only schools
tradition okay
uh I'd like to start tomorrow from this
point uh we're on page eight uh we're on
the sixth line and it'll be uh Justin
kappa's response to an objection that he
shouldn't really have used those
quotations and that they're not really
very relevant to this point okay
uh if I start going more you might get
into a new uh nominal existing thing
that didn't really that wasn't existing
before like okay
if I keep going
a few new normal objects okay
future when people ask you about how was
your trip to Sarah May and India you
probably have a lot of time with all
these extra talks that you brought
home and you'll be thinking about all
those extra nominal objects in your mind
and you'll they'll all come back to you
the cup of tea the foot on the step and
all those things
oh yeah
and then